hello I'm your host David Bernard
today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
cat state of subscription apps report
each episode in this series will explore
one crucial metric and share actionable
insights from Top subscription app
operators with me today Jackson
shuttleworth group product manager
retention team lead at dualingo on the
podcast I talk with Jackson about
dingo's datadriven approach to retention
how social connections dramatically
improved reactivation and why letting
users set the prefer notification time
backfires hey Jackson thanks so much for
joining me on the podcast today yeah
thank you for having me dude so I'm
really looking forward to talking about
reactivation and keeping users in the
app and getting them back when they've
left but for context duelingo is such a
huge company I did want to give
listeners just a little insight into
what you work on dayto day so duelingo I
manage our retention efforts this sits
within the growth or at duelingo so this
is focusing on how do we grow our user
base specifically focusing on daus and
so within retention a lot of this
focusing on the most habit forming
features in our app so you've probably
heard of the dualingo streak this is
what I spend a lot of time every day
thinking about how to better optimize
with some of the other teams Under My
Umbrella focusing on things like
notifications push notifications emails
things that are both helping keep the
user in the app and that's what we focus
most on is how do we get you to never
churn but then once we do churn or once
the user does churn how do we get them
back into the app as quickly as possible
because you learn that the longer the
the user has been away the harder it is
to get them to come home so in the
report we're not going to share usage
metrics we are going to be sharing
subscriber metrics and subscriber
reactivation metrics but what's going to
be fun chatting with you is that you're
not as focused on the subscriber
reactivation which it focused on the
user reactivation and ultimately that's
Upstream of the subscriber reactivation
if you ever have a hope to win somebody
back to your subscription you first need
to win them back to the app so let's
shout about that like what's your
philosophy around how to get people back
into the app the the easiest way to
retain a user is to not let them turn to
begin with and so a lot of the features
that you'll see on dualingo are really
focused on building that daily habit
even and and we've run so many
experiments on our streak even things
that have users spending one two days
away from the app
make it significantly more difficult to
get them to come back in two or three
days later so a lot of our focus is
getting users if they can use the app
each day to use it every day I will say
that again this team does manage things
like notifications emails this is a lot
of our power um just have taken a few
days off getting them back in the app we
send a series of seven notifications if
you for each day that you don't use the
app and so you take a day off we send
send you notification second day off we
sent you notification at seven days we
turn off our practice or Miner
notifications which are our most
powerful notification because the
additional value we get of continuing to
reach out to you after seven days is
significantly lower I honestly even by
day seven the efficacy is has dropped
significantly and so that is sort of an
insight into you can't wait till day
seven to get that user to come back into
the app you probably can't wait till day
five if they're not coming back by day
three or 4 again depending upon the use
case for us that's for a daily use app
that's definitely the case man it it is
just going to be tough sledding to get
them to come back for a lot of apps that
aren't as focused on daily use which I
think is a good portion of the folks who
will be listening is a golfing app where
you're going to go golfing two or three
times a month or even a fitness app
which maybe you're doing really well to
be working out three times a week for
the folks who have past that seven day
Mark who are more challenging I feel
like maybe that's more relatable to a
lot of the folks who are are going to be
listening to this how do you think about
those people who have have been out of
the app for seven days who are the kind
of harder problem we think about it
across a few different time scales and
I'll say the first one is the first few
weeks after we've lost you so we have
like a progress report type email that
goes out to users the fact that it's an
email is nice because it gives us
significantly more space for us to
highlight elements of your progress
report versus just to push notification
where we're really having to
rely heavily on you tapping into this to
go back to an app that maybe you've
uninstalled so here actually channel is
important and so this is nice because it
is a weekly progress comparison where
week to week we say hey how did you do
this week versus how you did last week
if you've taken a week or two off
obviously that's framed somewhat
negatively but what you could do is and
and there's all sorts of different copy
that we've tested there's ways to draw
attention to like hey have you taken a
break come back and jump in ory hey man
seems like a slow week how much you
going to learn this week There's
different ways to make that copy and
messaging to users either a little bit
passive aggressive or hopeful or like a
challenge and this is really important
what I'd say is like you got to test all
of these different copy variants one of
the things to do like we test so much
copy like a disgusting amount of copy
particularly with a lot of our
notification type work and different
users are different and you can have as
many hypothesis as you want about what
works you just got to test it a lot of
it is just engagement metrics that we're
showing you how much xp did you earn how
much time did you spend in there and
some of that's because it is more
complex for us to show you more like hey
you learned this word or you know like
the feasibility of that is is is higher
as we think about Roi what we've
realized is that like just showing a
user how much they've done and allowing
them to infer and using copy to support
it like hey look at all the stuff you've
done it's much easier and honestly gets
you know a lot of the bang to the buck
for dual lingo where you're obviously
using dualingo to learn a language make
better use your free time it's easier
for us to tell this Narrative of like
you use dualingo isn't that obvious
obviously a good thing this time you
spent but I think you know there's a lot
that you can do as for me the the the
product manager to just draw attention
to here's the activity in the a it is
necessarily a good thing don't you want
to come back and get more of that you
can Frame data lots of different ways to
make it seem motivating and I would
challenge your listeners to like really
look out because these users are J if
they're not compelled by your message
they're not going to come back so then
moving on to the the longer time span so
I guess that it was like the 7 to 30 day
and then like after 30-day is I guess
the next bucket yeah yeah so a few
different things I'll say one thing
that's that's hot on our mind is we do a
a big year review type similar to like a
Spotify wrapped where at the end of the
year we're showing you stats and
information about your learning and it's
super fun I you know recommend anybody
who's been on duelingo this year like go
check it out even if you were a user who
used it for a few days in April we can
still show you something and give you
value and give you value pretty much
immediately after reopening the app that
is awesome and exciting and makes you
laugh and makes you think like oh
actually hey I could I could use that
app again and so I think the more you
can frame some of these Outreach moments
even months later in a way that when the
user comes back they're getting
something delightful they're getting a
little endorphin rush it is something
fun and particularly if you can tie it
to them again the user that's used the
app for a few days in April isn't going
to have a lot of really high value
analysis we can give them we could still
make it a super delightful experience
and that might be what it takes to get
them
overd and using the app again and so I
think the more you can tie it to Tides
Outreach moments to either specific
times of year specific information What
can you deliver to the user in terms of
value and not just like here's a product
update much better performance though
when we can actually attach it to
something relatively personal speaking
of of performance are there any
campaigns that stick out in your mind
that's especially effective like leading
up to the summer after Co we said hey
are you traveling this summer is there
any like just knocked it out of the park
kind of thing that you recall specific
campaigns less so than there are
specific times of year that are always
really really important to us and and
it's exactly as you said none of this
should probably be all too surprising
because we try to build our campaigns
around the mental model that users have
or I'm using our product so like back to
school always very big people are going
back to school you want to start
learning again even like people who are
not in school you kind of get that
mindset of like going to class and so
that's a really big time for us we make
sure to Target that with messaging that
resonate same thing beginning of the
year New Year's resolutions we are
dueling goes often learning language
learning anything definitely a new user
resolution that folks have and it's
funny because that actually works quite
well with our year at review type
program where we're getting users back
at the end of the year hopefully some of
those users are sticking around at the
beginning of the year where then they're
making that commitment to hey I'm gonna
learn a language I'm back on dualingo
I'm just going to keep it up but again
for us it's less the actual to me anyway
less the actual creative and more how
are we targeting the right times of the
year with the right message how do you
think about data and experimentation in
relation to all of this I know I mean
dualing of ly does a ton of testing so
when you're thinking about these
reactivating users and winning users
back how do you think about it in terms
of data and making it more data informed
for dueling go notifications again be
email or push are a critical part of our
feature set and a critical driver of
growth for us so we have machine
learning driven systems that choose the
right notification copy for the right
user they optimize on their own I mean r
PM it's really nice you just kind of
like stick copy variants in there with
AI we probably won even have to do that
soon enough like yeah will stick and
then it optimizes which is great and if
once you have the kids you know or or
the the size and scale to do that
building a system like that is awesome
never sleep on copy and with
notifications it is like infinitely more
important to constantly be testing
because all it can rely on is that
subject line and maybe some preview copy
your push notification all can rely on
is what's in the title and what's in the
body
you don't have the whole feature set
that it's supporting it or the fact the
users in the app already like it's just
all copy it's all testing and so again
depends on the size of your population
but you can look at Open click through
open rates open rates or click through
rates again be it email or notification
I mean you can get I would guess
statting data pretty quickly but again I
just see a lot of companies I don't know
looking at notifications it's clear that
like there there's some that like all
right cool this notification worked
let's move on I mean our practice
reminder notification and we've been
exper on that experimenting on that
notifcation for six years for a PM that
loves experimentation it's beautiful to
see so really honing that message
because again I said this earlier these
users have churned you don't know what
they remember about their experience
there's a lot that you don't know about
this user this is the user you need to
experiment on almost more than any
because it's just less like you like
that you have a a good handle on what it
is that they like all of our scheduling
is smart although one of the funny
things about our scheduling that we
realized is that I think there's this
desire from company when you start when
you on board and you say hey when do you
want us to remind you in the morning in
the evening at this time what we realize
is that you know if as soon as you set a
time the likelihood that you were going
to be free at that time for perpetuity
which is what a lot of apps assume is
just zero like you all have busy lives
we all use these apps at different times
of day and what was always a winner for
us was scheduling the the next day's
notification for 23 and a half hours
after you practiced for the first time
that day and so we basically just were
always targeting when did you practice
the day before the next day so there is
a lot of and this doesn't seem smart
although we've tested a lot of different
strategies here and this is the one that
continues to win any other top tips for
getting people back one that's been an
interesting thread for us to pull on is
social in the app as it pertains to win
backs duelingo has been investing in our
app social network now for many years I
think we're at like 55 or 60% of our
users have a friend on the app and these
aren't all like my mom for instance uses
dualingo we we're friends in the app oh
that's a great L back man mom in the app
like hey Jackson yeah well whenever my
mom lives in the street it cuts
particularly deep so one of the things
that we've again threads we've been
pulling on is getting users to resurrect
each other so if you have a friend who's
been gone for months and months
prompting the user to hey get them to
come back and this is one of our best
performing Resurrection campaigns or one
back campaigns just because he it feels
more personal it's not dualingo saying
hey David come back it's Jackson saying
hey come back and learn with me and then
what's cool is now we have other
features in the app so one feature we'
recently launched punched as friend
streaks it's a way for you to learn with
somebody else now we have a social
feature set that when you can get this
person back into the app now that
there's been a personal appeal made you
can ease them into a more social
experience with that person so it's a
nice way to pair the outof app
communication with the inapp experience
but even for folks that it's like again
the random person that you find on your
leaderboard still a much higher
clickthrough rate for there people that
you've never met in real life even
messages back messages from from those
folks still perform better as we're
wrapping up anything else you want to
share yes if any of this sounds
interesting for you to work on we are
hiring actually we're hiring both for my
team looking for a senior to lead PM who
wants to work in Pittsburgh helping
drive a lot of our retention efforts so
again the streak excites you do that
professionally and then the other area
is we're starting to build a
notifications team so looking for
a senior to lead PM in New York who
wants us to help build out you know an
even smarter more robust and thoughtful
notifications platform so this was a a
very relevant discussion for us today
and if you find it relevant to to what
you like to think about definitely reach
out awesome well thanks so much for
joining me today it's so insightful a
lot of really fun stuff thank you yeah
of
course thanks so much for listening if
you have a minute please leave a review
in your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub